hello everyone my name is greg neither
staff welcome everyone to episode 10 of
the tactics game in unity in this
episode we will move character around
the map taking into account his maximum
distance of movement
let's start by defining maximum distance
our character can move
so select the character open character
script here we want to add movement
points field of type float
with default value 50
one square in the grid will cost you 10
points to move true
so 50 points will mean your character
can move through five cells on the grid
if there is no obstruction or difficulty
rain
the reason why we use the factor of 10
is that this will allow us to simplify
the calculation of difficult terrain
later on in the tutorial
for example moving through the forest
will cause two times more movement
points
so it will cost 20 movement points
therefore your character will be able to
move two squares
before exhausting if he is moving
through 4 styles and because he will
have 10 left overs for move points he
can move through one additional clear
tile
you have a field for movement points in
the character component so if you want
to increase this distance of movement of
your character you need to change this
field
now we want to calculate all the squares
our character can reach to do this we
will we will be using our pathfinding
but instead of calculating the path to
the specific position we will be
calculating for each node around the
character to determine where this
character can reach with his movement
action
open pathfinding we are going to utilize
part of the find path method but we will
redesign it to calculate all the
reachable nodes instead of finding paths
between two specific nodes
create a new method called calculate
workable nodes past starting position
total amount of move points
your character have and reference to the
list of pass notes called to highlight
we will use this list to highlight all
the reachable nodes
i will not be describing everything in
details because i already did get
through this pathfinding script with you
in previous episodes i will only explain
changes
we will be doing
now we will be dissecting the find path
method for our new method copy start
node copy both open and close list
copy the while cycle
and get the current node
now we don't need this part we're not
going to determine the most efficient
node to calculate based on f value
because we're not trying to aim for any
specific directions we're spreading
across all the possible directions our
character can move we are calculating
every node around the character
remove the current node out of open list
and add current node to close list
then skip the end node destination reach
check because we don't have destination
is reached check
we will need to read all the neighboring
nodes so copy this neighbor node cycle
now we need to cycle through all the
neighbor nodes and calculate the cost to
reach this node
then if the move cost to this node is
more than move points available to this
character
then skip this node because this
character can't reach this node
we don't need h value and don't have end
node so remove it
so let's go through the code quickly one
more time we get the starting position
and based on that we get the start node
the node of origin the node where our
character is standing right now
then we add the start node into the
open list and start the cycle which will
be cycling until we exhaust all the
nodes out of open list
which will mean we have calculated all
possible nodes our character can reach
then we determine all the neighboring
nodes around the currently selected node
for calculations
then we go through all the neighboring
nodes by doing checks for it being
already calculated for it being workable
calculating move cost into this node
then if the move cost to this node is
not higher than available amount of
character move points we add this
neighbor node into open list
then we pick up the very first node in
the open list and repeat the process
until there is no more nodes in the open
list
meanwhile closed list will contain all
the nodes which is already past the
calculation
and is reachable or workable by our
character so we can use the closed list
to highlight all the nodes our character
can reach
so add the whole clause list into the
past to highlight list using add range
good
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
now on the move character let's on the
start calling create calculate workable
terrain
inside call calculate workable nodes and
pass target character
get the character component on the
target character and pass it
movement points
create a list and pass this list to the
calculate workable nodes
good this will calculate the workable
nodes and we can highlight them which we
will do now
create serialized field grid highlight
assign reference to our character in the
editor and to the grid highlight
enable the move character and disable
the grid control
open grid highlight script and comment
out the testing part of the code
okay we have an out of order execution
error
before we start fixing this let's clean
our tabs in visual studio
leave only pathfinding and move
character if you don't have them opened
open them in the editor
so what is happening
this start is being executed before this
start and because the pathfinding in it
initiates the whole passing grid
trying to work with pathfinding before
initiating it cause an error so we need
to force the order of execution of
pathfinding to be before the move
character script
this way it will ensure that our
pathfinding is prepped before attempting
to pass finding on it
let's test this
ok this removes the error but there is
no movement points
oh of course i did not call highlight
with the list of workable nodes
now we have the issue the highlight
takes
position to highlight on the grid in the
list of vector 2 ins
instead we want to pass past nodes
so let's create an overload of this
method which will do the same but use
pass nodes instead
and another out of order execution
problem this one let's fix by changing
start into the awake awake always
executed before start but if you have
multiple away calls they will be
executed in the order of execution
similar to the start and in that case
you can end up in the similar situation
as this bunch of starts
so the accepted idea is that you use
awake if you initiating of the class
has get component and
initialization of the lists and classes
meanwhile preliminary calculations
should be done in the start instead of
awake
let's test this as you can see our night
girl highlight all the positions she can
reach
now what we want to do is when we click
on the map we should start moving
towards the position
if we determine that she in the matter
of fact can reach it
for this we will create a new method in
the pathfinding called traceback which
will use calculated data we have made to
determine where our character can move
to trace back to the origin
and then move this character to the
selected destination using traced back
pass
this method will return the list of past
nodes it will get the selected character
as a parameter and x and y position of
the selected node to move towards
create the list of nodes then if we
click on something what is outside the
boundaries
return out of this method with null
actually move this check above the list
initialization
get the endpoint pass node using the
position we passed then move back to the
character by using the parent nodes
actually we don't need selected
character as a parameter at all here
what's going to happen
is because we have calculated everything
already now the only thing we need to do
is to move backwards using the
calculated data and this is what we're
doing here
open move character script and now we
need to get the path using traceback
method we just created in the update
when you press left mouse button call
trace back instead of find pass
because the path is traced back reverse
the pass
okay let's do this
she is moving but not animating
forgot to add character animator to the
character prefabs my bad
now if you click somewhere the character
should move into that direction but if
you click one more time the character
will move back to her original position
then pass towards the destination
this is normal because after we done
moving we need to clean up the
pathfinding grid and update the
vocabulary terrain to determine where
your character can reach from a new
position
we will do this in the next episode
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any idea about
code please leave your comment below if
you're interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe if you
want to support further you can find my
patreon in the description special thank
you to andrew v long and this old harsh
duel
for their generous support with best
regards see in the next episode
you